what's up my piano friends i've been
playing and teaching piano for over 15
years now and there are five things i
absolutely wish i would have known
before i started learning mistakes that
caused me years of pain and frustration
that it actually could have solved very
easily if i just knew what i was doing
and i'm gonna work back from number five
all the way to the most important thing
number one so make sure you stick around
to the end of the video for that
otherwise you'll be so frustrated on
piano you'll end up like this guy
rule number one never smash your piano
with a sledgehammer this is bad form
it's much more efficient to use a
baseball bat preferably a metal one you
can get a lot more leverage that way
i'm kidding i'm kidding all right on to
the real rule number one and that's i
wish i would have started learning piano
learning to read chord shapes instead of
sheet music see most people on youtube
are trying to learn songs with outdated
sheet music and this is a very slow way
of learning because they force you to
learn each individual note one at a time
that's like trying to read a book one
letter at a time it takes forever
instead we can group letters together to
form words and we can read words much
faster than letters similarly instead of
memorizing individual notes we can group
notes together to form chord shapes to
learn 10 times faster so let's say we're
trying to learn all of me by john legend
instead of learning all of these notes
with the sheet music we can group them
together into four chord shapes we can
find these chord shapes using a simple
google search and this simple cheat
sheet alright so if we look at the cheat
sheet and i'll show you where to get
this in a sec let's just take four
chords so first e minor it looks like
this
then c major looks like this
then g major looks like this
and finally d major looks like this
and if we just repeat these same four
chords over and over you can play
hundreds of your favorite songs on piano
let me show you
what would i do without your smart mouth
drawing me in and you kicking me out say
something i'm giving up on you
whoa
listen to your heart
[Music]
like a melody in my head that i can't
keep up got me singing like isn't that
way cooler than learning like you know
mary had a little lamb using sheet music
and ironically it's just as easy to
learn if you have the cheat sheet that
shows you the chord shapes so if you
want more info on this style of learning
and the chord shapes cheat sheet i'll
put a link to that video in the upper
right and in the description all right
on to tip number two and that's getting
hands together coordination in other
words how do i get my dang left and
right hand to just work together now
this is the biggest struggle almost
every single beginner has because of one
simple reason they're trying to focus on
everything at the same time and that's
what i did when i was first trying to
learn piano now most beginners they try
to learn hands coordination while
they're learning songs so now they have
to focus on the notes the rhythm the
dynamics the sharps and flats of speed
and they have to get hands together at
the same time and so they end up super
frustrated and start smashing their
keyboard with a sledgehammer instead
it's way easier to have a set of hand
independence exercises where the notes
and dynamics and everything else stay
very very simple and you can focus on
just getting hands together coordination
and you can isolate and master that
skill until it becomes automatic and
then the exercises slowly and gradually
get more difficult until you're playing
song level exercises hands together no
problem and then when you go back to
your song it'll be very very easy to get
your hands together coordination because
you've already drilled it in separately
doesn't that make way more sense than
trying to learn everything at the same
time anyway if you want to get the hands
together exercises i'll put the link to
that video in the upper right and in the
description which brings me to tip
number three i wish i would have started
learning to play piano by ear right from
the get-go and i know what you're
thinking you're thinking zack i don't
have musical ears i'm tone deaf get out
of here with that nonsense we're gonna
do a test right now and if you can pass
this test it proves that you can play by
ear okay so let's go to the keyboard
let's just take three notes c d and e
all right but we're just gonna call
these to make it even simpler one two
and three
what i'm gonna do is i'm gonna cover up
my hand and i'm gonna play a pattern and
i want you to listen to the pattern and
try to figure out which numbers i'm
playing so for example if i play this
[Music]
that would just be the pattern one
two
one
three
all right got it all right i'm gonna
cover up my hand now and listen to the
pattern
[Music]
all right i'm going to play it one more
time comment below if you think you know
what it is
[Music]
okay so that was just a pattern one
two
three
one did you get it right all right let's
try one more you ready
[Music]
all right try to figure out the notes
one more time put your answer in the
comments ready
[Music]
all right so the answer is
one
two
three
all right let's try one more example
this one is gonna be a bit more tricky
so i'm gonna give you a clue we're going
to start on the note 3
all right you ready i'm going to play it
right now ready
[Music]
one more time let me know in the
comments if you think you know what it
is
all right rewind the video if you have
to and get your answer
all right so the correct answer is
three
two
one
well guess what that is that's actually
part of the song all of me by john
legend check this out all your curves
and all your edges
and then it repeats
all your perfect
so you literally just learned to play
part of all of me by john legend by ear
with zero formal training and i know
you're thinking you're thinking okay
zach that was only three notes what
about the rest of them well the process
to learning to play by ear is you take
these three notes and you actually spend
three or four days on the exercises the
play by ear exercises with these three
notes until they're absolutely rock
solid and you know them like the back of
your hand then after you do that you add
two more notes these two notes
and you learn these five notes and this
is pretty easy because you already have
the first three notes rock solid in your
fingers and then eventually you add you
know two more notes and eventually you
learn the black notes so that you have
12 notes learned to play by ear these 12
notes and then it's very easy to kind of
copy and paste these notes up octaves up
the keyboard and you can literally play
any song by ear it's a very gradual and
systematic process and anybody can learn
to play by ear in three to four months
if you do the exercises every day anyway
if you want more info on that i'll put a
link in the upper right and in the
description alright if you like what
you're learning so far go ahead and
smash that like button really helps
boost my self-esteem and then all my
friends will think i'm cool because i
have a bunch of likes in my video just
kidding but seriously smash the like
button it really helps out the channel
all right on to tip number four and
that's using a song mapping chart and
this is gonna help you learn songs 10
times faster see learning a song is
actually pretty simple right we just
break our song up into sections intro
verse chorus etc we have to do four
things for each section first we have to
learn the notes then we have to speed it
up from slow to fast then we have to
memorize it and then we have to add
expressiveness and emotion to that
section of the song and if you do these
four steps for every section of the song
and you cross off all of these boxes
boom you have your entire song learned
does that make sense so when you sit
down at the piano with this chart let's
say on day one you sit down at the piano
and you learn the notes of the intro so
you just go ahead and you just cross off
this box maybe you learn verse one of
the notes as well you cross off this box
and maybe for the first chorus you learn
the right hand but you're not quite
there with the left hand so you put in a
little note that says right hand good
here and now day two you sit down at the
piano to practice and this is when it
starts getting really powerful now if
you're not using this chart what most
beginners do is they just start back
from the beginning and they relearn the
intro which is a huge waste of time
because you've already learned the intro
and verse one but if you're using your
song mapping chart you can look at your
chart and say okay i'm good for the
intro and verse one let me start with
the chorus one i'm i'm good for the
right hand already so let me just
practice the left hand and then you can
start working your left hand until your
left hand is good and once it's good you
can cross off this box and then maybe
you cross off you know you work verse
two you get this one good you get chorus
too good on day two and maybe the intro
you know you work on the speed and you
get it to full speed and then day three
you know you sit back down your piano
you say hey the intro i heard it have it
learned and i already have it sped up
i'm not gonna work the intro but maybe
i'll speed up verse one and maybe you do
that first and then maybe you work on
learning the bridge and you cross this
off and then maybe you know course one
you try to get it up to full speed but
maybe it's not quite there yet so you
don't cross off this box yet you leave
it unchecked and as you do this day
after day you'll have a complete
overview of exactly which sections of
your song you need to work on and which
sections you don't have to and
eventually of course you'll cross off
all these boxes and once all these boxes
are crossed off boom you'll have every
section of your song learned sped up
memorized and added expressiveness and
emotion and boom you're done with your
song and what i see all the time from
beginners who don't use this kind of
chart is they have their intro on their
first verse really really good and it
sounds awesome and then the rest of
their song sucks because they never
practice it they every day they sit down
and they work on the stuff that they
already know just because it's at the
beginning so this chart gives you this
kind of road map of exactly what you
need to work on so that you can learn
songs way way faster anyway this thing
is an absolute game changer if you want
to get the pdf of a blank chart that
looks like this that way you can fill in
your own sections and you can cross off
the boxes i'll put the link to that in
the top right and in the description if
you want to use this to learn your next
piece of music alright finally on to tip
number five and that's working on your
technique right from the get go now most
students think technique is super boring
because nobody showed them why it's so
powerful and important to have rock
solid technique because good technique
can solve certain issues almost
instantly on the keyboard let me show
you an example now a lot of students
struggle with what i call weak pinky
syndrome where they can play their first
four fingers just fine
but their pinky always feels weak and
uncoordinated maybe you have this
problem right now most beginners try to
solve this with brute force right and
they think okay my pinky is weak i just
need to do these you know finger
exercises
to make it strong and strengthen my
pinky and they spend years trying to
quote unquote strengthen their pinky and
ironically they just end up drilling in
bad habits they're an absolute nightmare
to correct in the future instead let me
show you how easy this is to solve with
good technique now if you look at your
hand you'll notice your middle three
fingers are very long and this way when
you curve your fingers and make them
nice and strong when you're playing it's
very easy
to play these three nice and strong but
your pinky if you curve it
you can't reach the note right if your
pinky is nice and strong and curved
you're literally going to miss the note
on the keyboard and that's because
people play with a straight wrist now
all we have to do to solve this is move
our wrist down and out and now look at
our pinky
nice and curved and strong
so all we got to do to fix weak pinky
syndrome is rotate our wrists down and
out when we're playing our pinky and if
you practice this for three to four days
you can solve weak pinky syndrome almost
instantly without quote-unquote
strengthening your pinky because you're
actually playing with good technique how
easy is that but guess what there are a
ton of these little subtle movement
patterns that make a huge difference in
your playing if you're interested in
learning those and getting the exercises
to drill those in rock solid into your
hands click this video to master your
technique or if you're more interested
in learning songs from the radio using
the chord shades cheat sheet that we
talked about earlier click this video
and learn that happy practicing and i'll
see in the next one